<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>My Lord Newarks speech to the trained-bands of Nottingham-shire at Newark, 13. July. 1642. Concerning His Maiesties commission of array.</title>
            <title>Speech to the trained-bands of Nottingham-shire at Newark, 13 July, 1642</title>
            <author>Dorchester, Henry Pierrepont, Marquis of, 1606-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1919A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E200_52</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50874297</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50874297</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157586</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81629)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157586)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 35:E200[52])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>My Lord Newarks speech to the trained-bands of Nottingham-shire at Newark, 13. July. 1642. Concerning His Maiesties commission of array.</title>
                  <title>Speech to the trained-bands of Nottingham-shire at Newark, 13 July, 1642</title>
                  <author>Dorchester, Henry Pierrepont, Marquis of, 1606-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page contains printers' device (McK. 422, with rose).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Commissions of array --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157586:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>My Lord Nevvarks SPEECH To the Trained-bands of <hi>Nottingham-ſhire</hi> at <hi>Newark,</hi> 13. July<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1642.</p>
            <p>Concerning His MAIESTIES Commiſſion of Array.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:157586:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:157586:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Tudor rose</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Scottish thistle</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>French fleur-de-lis</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Irish harp</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen, and my good Conntrey-men all,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe Noble Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and my ſelfe have called you together by vertue of His Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of Array directed to us, I ſhall acquaint you with the grounds and reaſons of it, which are theſe, the defence of His moſt ſacred Perſon, of your Liberties, Laws, Religion, and the juſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:157586:3"/> Theſe are the ends of this Commiſsion, and of all His Majeſties actions and endeavors, they tend hither as to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Centre and place of reſt; I know herein you eaſily beleeve me, the leaſt doubt cannot remain with them that have ſo often had his Royall word, his ſolemne and frequent proteſtations to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and the Word of a King is ſacred as His Perſon, what then are His ſolemne Proteſtations?</p>
            <p>I hope this is the fartheſt jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney you ſhall take, and that your Countrey ſhall be the onely Spheare wherin you are to move, I am ſure His Majeſty heartily deſires it ſhould be ſo; But if there be urgent and neceſſarily occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that you muſt goe further, I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:157586:3"/> will accompany you, and not any ſhall be expoſed to that hazzard I will not be my ſelfe; your trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhall be mine, your danger mine, all fortunes I will partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate with you, and my care of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of you ſhall be equall to that I ſhal have of my ſelf I ſhould have been glad to have found any where, ſuch zeale and readineſſe to ſerve the King; but rejoyce much more to find them here, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you my Countreymen, in this place, the place of my birth, and my affections; It ſhould argue ſome diffidence I had of you to perſwade you to perſwade you to obedience and loyalty to your Prince, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I ſhould loſe time in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when I already ſee your hearts full of them, and well may
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:157586:4"/> they be ſo to him that is ſo careful and tender of the good of you, So gracious a Prince, as unexampled in vertues as in Royalty; beſides I ſhould but lay open my owne folly in thinking any Arguments could be more prevalent and of greater efficacy with you then thoſe I have already named, your religion, the ſafety &amp; preſervation of your Prince, of your Lawes, and Liberties, and of all that is deere and neere unto you, to theſe I may adde, the faithfull keeping of thoſe religious Oaths and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations you have taken; with whom theſe would not be power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full I am ſure nothing under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven could, no not Heaven it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>I have acquainted the KING, and fully, with your forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:157586:4"/> to ſerve him, and told him that this Countrey hath beene onely remoter from His Perſon, but as neere to him in heart as <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> and that in our dutifull affections to Him we will not be ſecond to any ſubjects He hath. I have no more to trouble you with, you may all now depart e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one to his own home, where I pray God you may happily live, and enioy the benefit of thoſe good Lawes the care of former times hath tranſferred to you, and the goodneſſe of His Maieſty hath beſtowed, and is ſtill ready to beſtow more upon you.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
